Sunday, April 29, 1945, one week before the end of World War II in Europe.
45th Infantry Division of the Seventh United States Army liberates Dachau, the first camp
concentration camp built by the Nazi government. Soldiers not only smell human excrement,
but also decomposing bodies, which makes many of them cry or vomit when
find piles of incredibly malnourished corpses, more than 30 train cars full of
thousands of corpses and 30 thousand survivors, most of them severely emaciated,
that look like walking skeletons. Some of them were even subjected to cruel and painful
pseudomedical experiments carried out by one of the most sadistic and morally depraved Nazi doctors
corrupt. His name is Sigmund Rascher.
Sigmund Rascher was born on February 12, 1909 in Munich, then part of the German Empire.
He was the third son of Dr. Hanns-August Rascher, whose brother was the musician Sigurd
Rascher. His father was a committed supporter of the anthroposophist Rudolf Steiner and in fact in 1921
participated in Steiner's first medical course. The young Sigmund attended the
First Waldorf School in Stuttgart, a school based on the anthroposophical approach
Steiner's approach to education. He was influenced by Ehrenfried Pfeiffer, who believed in
the influence of cosmic rhythms on life processes. He completed his secondary education
in Konstanz in 1930 and the same year he began studying medicine at the University of Freiburg.
On January 30, 1933, Adolf Hitler was appointed Chancellor of Germany by the
President Paul von Hindenburg and, a few months later, Sigmund Rascher joined
to the Nazi Party. After completing his preliminary examination, he worked for his father,
now divorced, in Basel, Switzerland, and continued his medical studies there. In October 1934,
He returned to Germany to study at the Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich.
In 1936 he passed the state medical examination there, obtained his doctorate and joined the SA.
That same year he met his future wife, Karoline Diehl, a former cabaret singer,
who had been widowed in 1929, since her first husband, the theatre director Oskar Diehl,
had passed away. Karoline, who was born in 1893, was 15 years older than Rascher and had
valuable contacts at the highest levels of politics. In the early days of the Party
Nazi, helped Heinrich Himmler and from then on maintained contact with the future Reichsführer of
the SS. Thanks to her close relationship with Himmler, who was allegedly her former lover,
was able to offer Rascher opportunities for career advancement within the Nazi state.
At his recommendation, Himmler received Rascher in person for the first time in April 1939.
A week after his first meeting with Himmler, Rascher presented a document entitled
"Report on the development and solution of some of the tasks assigned to the Reichsführer
during a discussion held on April 24, 1939." Rascher became involved in the test
of a plant extract as a cancer treatment. Professor Kurt Blome,
Deputy Minister of Health and Plenipotentiary for Cancer Research,
was in favor of testing the extract on mice, but Rascher insisted
use human test subjects. Himmler sided with Rascher and established
a human cancer testing station at the Dachau concentration camp.
Dachau was the first concentration camp created by the Nazi government in March 1933,
less than two months after Hitler became chancellor. During the first year,
The camp had a capacity of 5,000 prisoners. At first,
The internees were mainly German communists, social democrats,
trade unionists and other political opponents of the Nazi regime. However, over time, other
Groups were also interned at Dachau, such as Jehovah's Witnesses, Roma and Sinti,
homosexuals, repeat offenders, as well as the so-called "asocials", whom the
regime imprisoned them because they could not or would not find paid employment.
During the early years, relatively few Jews were interned at Dachau, and in general,
They only ended up inside if they belonged to one of the groups mentioned or had served sentences.
from prison after being convicted of violating the Nuremberg Laws of 1935,
who incorporated Nazi ideas about race into legislation. In early 1937, the SS,
Using prisoner labor, they began to build a large complex of buildings in the
land of the original camp. The prisoners were forced to do this work,
starting with the destruction of the old munitions factory, under conditions
terrible. Construction was officially completed in mid-August 1938.
One month before World War II, which began on September 1, 1939 with the invasion
A German from Poland, Rascher had been recruited into the Luftwaffe, the German air force.
Due to Rascher's servile and ingratiating treatment of Himmler, his connections were so
so strong that practically all of his superiors trembled with fear before the scheming Rascher,
who consequently occupied a position of enormous power.
In October 1939, Rascher transferred from the SA to the SS and to marry Karoline he needed
Himmler's approval. This was part of the strict control and regulation of private life
of the SS members, as Himmler intended to ensure that their marriages would be
conform to the racial and ideological principles of the Nazi regime. Due to Karoline's age,
Himmler was initially opposed to the two marrying, as it was not expected that
a marriage with numerous children would occur. The Nazi regime encouraged the birth of children
considered "racially valuable" to increase the "Aryan" population of Germany.
In 1939, Karoline and Rascher had an illegitimate child and when Karoline reported once again
that she was pregnant again, Himmler finally authorized the marriage, which took place in July
1942. Himmler supported the couple and, after having their second child, transferred 165 marks to them.
of the Reich every month. He also sent them packages with fruit, chocolate, and other gifts. Karoline
He returned the favor with family photos and asked for Rascher to be given a better job. Rascher
He also frequently wrote to Himmler requesting money, tax reductions,
fresh fruit, furniture, fruit juices, a new apartment and even slave maids.
Rascher suggested that high-altitude and low-altitude experiments be performed.
pressure in humans. While attending an aeronautical medicine course in Munich,
He wrote a letter to Himmler in which he said that his course included research on flights to
high altitude and regretted that human trials could not be carried out,
since such experiments were very dangerous and no one volunteered for them. Rascher
He asked Himmler to make human subjects available to him, stating quite frankly
that the experiments could prove fatal, but that previous tests carried out with
monkeys had not been satisfactory. The letter was answered by Rudolf Brandt,
Himmler's adjutant, who informed Rascher that prisoners would be made available.
Rascher wrote to Brandt to ask for permission to carry out his experiments at Dachau,
and plans for the experiments were developed at a conference
early 1942, attended by Rascher and members of the Luftwaffe Medical Service.
Experiments were carried out in the spring and summer of the same year, using a chamber
portable pressure chamber supplied by the Luftwaffe. The victims were locked in the chamber,
whose internal pressure was reduced to a level corresponding to very high altitudes. The
pressure could be altered very quickly, which allowed Rascher to simulate the conditions that
would experience a pilot in free fall from an altitude without oxygen. After seeing a report of
one of the fatal experiments, Himmler commented that if a subject survived such treatment,
should be "pardoned" to life imprisonment. Rascher, however, responded to Himmler
that the victims to date had been simply Poles and Soviets,
and believed that they should not be given any kind of amnesty. Of the 200 subjects,
80 died directly from the experiment and the rest were murdered.
Rascher also carried out so-called "freezing experiments" on behalf of
the Luftwaffe with 300 test subjects without their consent. The experiments were carried out
carried out at Dachau after the high-altitude tests had been completed. The purpose
was to determine the best way to warm up the German pilots who had been forced
descended into the North Sea and suffered hypothermia. Rascher's victims were
forced to remain naked outdoors in freezing weather for 14 hours or kept
in a tank of ice water for three hours, measuring their pulse and internal temperature through
of a series of electrodes. Then attempts were made to warm the victims by different methods,
the most common and successful one is immersion in hot water; at least one witness,
assistant in some of these proceedings, later testified that some victims were
thrown into boiling water to reheat. Himmler attended some of the experiments
and told Rascher that he should go to the North Sea region and find out how people
common there warmed victims of extreme cold. Himmler is reported to have said that he thought
that "a fisherwoman could take her half-frozen husband to bed and revive him that way
way" and added that everyone believed that "animal heat" had a different effect
to artificial heat. Four Roma women were sent from the concentration camp
from Ravensbrück and an attempt was made to warm him by placing the hypothermic victim between two naked women.
Rascher also experimented with the effects of Polygal, a substance made from pectin.
beetroot and apple, which helped blood clotting. He predicted that the preventive use of
Polygal tablets would reduce bleeding from gunshot wounds sustained during combat or
during surgery. Subjects were given a Polygal tablet and shot in the neck
or chest, or their limbs were amputated without anesthesia. Rascher published an article about
their experience with the use of Polygal, without detailing the nature of the human trials and also
He created a company to manufacture the substance, whose staff was made up of prisoners.
Between July and September 1944, other experiments on human beings were carried out at Dachau.
humans, in which prisoners were subjected to tests on the potability of seawater.
Doctors forced about 90 Roma prisoners to drink only seawater and,
At the same time, they were deprived of food. The Roma prisoners became so dehydrated that,
It is said that they would lick the floor after scrubbing it to get a drop of fresh water.
experiments caused enormous pain and suffering and resulted in serious bodily injury.
Rascher, who also allegedly collected human skin to make saddles,
was one of Himmler's favorites, but this was about to change in late 1943.
In an attempt to please Himmler by demonstrating that population growth could be accelerated if
the reproductive age of women was extended, Rascher made public the fact that his wife,
Karoline had given birth to three children even after she turned 48,
and Himmler used a photograph of Rascher's family as propaganda material. However,
During her fourth "pregnancy", Karoline Rascher was arrested while attempting to kidnap a baby.
A subsequent investigation revealed that her other three children had been bought or kidnapped.
In addition to acting as an accomplice in the kidnappings of the three babies, Rascher was also charged with
financial irregularities, the murder of his former laboratory assistant, and fraud
scientist. In December 1943, Rascher's laboratory assistant and housekeeper,
Julie Muschler, who had once lived in an apartment with the Raschers,
disappeared during a mountain trip with his partner.
When his body was found in April 1944, both Raschers came under strong suspicion.
of murder. Himmler, enraged that the Raschers had taken advantage of his trust,
had both of them sent to concentration camps without trial. Sigmund was sent
to Buchenwald and Karoline was sent to Ravensbrück. Both were held
in bunkers designated for special prisoners. Karoline, 51, was executed by hanging in
Ravensbrück at the end of April 1945. Her husband remained in Buchenwald after his arrest in 1944,
until the camp's evacuation in April 1945, and was then taken to Dachau. Sigmund
Rascher was 36 years old when he was executed on April 26 by direct order of Himmler,
just three days before the camp was liberated by American troops.
Rascher was killed by an SS officer who shot him through the door of
observing the cell and the delivery of food and then kicked him
on the body while saying: "Pig, now you have the punishment you deserve."
No tears were shed for Sigmund Rascher.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to give me a thumbs up
like to subscribe and click on the notification bell to
Don't miss our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel